Now,
果然
this is getting much more interesting.
这样就有意思多了
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
right here in the imperial court,
朝堂之上
your insolent actions defy
你胆敢肆意妄为
all sense of propriety,
简直是目无王法
a betrayal of your duty as a subject!
枉为人臣
The emperor is utterly incapable.
天子不为
The realm is in disarray.
四海难安
Chancellor Lai
来中丞
has been devoted to the empire.
一心为国
If he is facing injustice,
若得不公
we will not tolerate it!
我等不服
You betray your loyalty and honor.
辜恩背义
You treacherous ones!
你们这些乱臣贼子
How dare you speak so brazenly!
胆敢大放厥词
A woman's seizure of the throne, now
牝鸡司晨
that is the true calamity of the empire!
才是大苍之祸
Excellent!
好啊
The traitors have all revealed themselves.
都出来了
Now I shall see,
那哀家倒要看看
who exactly are the
究竟是谁
true calamity of the empire!
是这大苍之祸
Guards!
来人
Why not let me give it a go?
不如让我来试试
Look closely,
看看
these are our
这就是我大苍的
Palace Guards!
御前千牛卫
I have long heard that the Imperial Guard
早就听说
and the Imperial Inspectorate
这内卫府和御察司
are in collusion.
沆瀣一气
To my surprise, the Palace Guards
没承想
have also allied with Lai Luozhi.
这千牛卫也投靠了来党
Her Highness' been ill for quite some time.
太皇太后久病
Perhaps she has become a bit muddled.
许是糊涂了
What needs to be said,
该说什么
what actions to take,
该做什么
I still have to remind her of it.
还要我来提醒一下才是
Does Your Highness truly have nothing
太皇太后当真没有话
to address the officials?
要对群臣讲
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
bringing troops to besiege the palace,
你竟敢带兵围宫
your ambition to usurp is evident!
意图谋反
God's decree is clear,
天命攸归
It truly reflects the will of the people!
实乃人心所向
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
this is outrageous!
你放肆
Who would have imagined,
想不到啊
the Empress Dowager would actually
太皇太后竟还当真
be determined to fight to the bitter end.
要誓死一搏
Alas, it was
可惜了
unnecessary for it to come to this.
本可不必如此
Now that it has come to this,
事到如今
you surely understand
你也知道
how to draft
该如何写
the abdication edict, don't you?
这让位诏书了吧
Preposterous!
荒唐
What qualifications do you possess
你有什么资格
to inherit the throne?
能继承一统之位
What if I do possess such qualifications?
倘若我有这资格呢
You should accept the mandate of heaven,
当应天受命
and uphold the ultimate authority!
继天立极
Like a wolf in sheep's clothing,
真是狼子野心啊
their true intentions are malicious!
其心可诛
Enough of this noise!
聒噪
Drag these stubborn individuals
把这些迂腐
out of my sight!
都给我拖出去
Rip out their tongues!
割了他们的舌头
Shen Du.
沈渡
What are you waiting for?
还不动手
Aspiring to the throne?
你想坐这个位置
Delusional!
还不够格
Stand by for further instructions!
金吾卫
I, Shen Du of the Imperial Guard
内卫府沈渡
have scrutinized the Palace Guards
已彻查金吾卫
[and eliminated the conspirators.]
肃清其中谋逆
[I'll lead the forces to defend the]
今日领兵护圣
sovereign and seize the traitors!
只为擒拿反贼
The Shen Family has suffered
沈家上下几十条
the loss of dozens.
枉死的人命
Do you not wish
难道你不想
to avenge their deaths?
为他们报仇了
Think of your father, Shen Bingzhu;
想想你父亲沈秉烛
do you not want to restore his honor?!
你就不想为他平反了
I will uncover the truth myself,
真相我自会查清
and bring justice back to the Shen Family!
还我沈家一个公道
You are unworthy to stand
你与我为伍
as my brother-in-arms!
不配
So,
所以
you suspect that
依你的推测
the Fire Moth Sect has secretly
这些年火蛾门
thrived and expanded over the years
悄无生息地滋养壮大
with the aid of someone within the court,
是因为朝中有人在协助
and that someone
这个人
is most likely Lai Luozhi?
极可能是来罗织
While there is no concrete evidence,
虽无实证
the signs strongly suggest
但种种迹象表明
that Lai Luozhi
来罗织与此事
is involved.
脱不开干系
They are eyeing the supreme authority,
火蛾门觊觎朝堂
attempting to manipulate the weaknesses
妄图拿捏
of Princess Ying and others,
永安公主等人的把柄
stirring up royal conflicts.
挑唆皇室纷争
It's clear that the mastermind behind this
可见背后之人
is deeply concealed.
所藏至深
And he's even scheming grander schemes!
图谋更甚
He's bold enough to tamper with
连朝堂管控的丹砂
the court-regulated cinnabar;
都敢染指
Your speculation
可以肯定你的推测
is highly likely to be accurate.
是十有八九啊
What are your thoughts?
你意下如何
The enemy lurks in the shadows.
敌在暗
It would be wise to seize the opportunity
不如顺势而为
and lead them into a trap.
请君入瓮
Very well.
好
I shall see,
我倒要看看
what results
你这瓮中捉鳖
your trapping will yield!
会有什么效果
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
Shen Du has gone to
这是沈渡
great lengths to obtain this
特意从金乌部落
rare medicinal herb from the Jinwu Tribe.
寻来的灵药
He discreetly arranged for its delivery,
暗中派人送入宫的
claiming it's effective for your condition.
说是正对此症
Please take it; you will be well
喝了
in just half a month.
半月便能好
[A clever tactic to maneuver in secrecy.]
好一招暗度陈仓
You feigned loyalty to me,
你假意投诚
even risking your own life
竟不惜用自己
and those around you!
和身边的人来赌
Instead of claiming I lured
与其说我假意迷惑
you into confusion,
不如说是你的自大
it's your overconfidence that walked you
引你掉入
into the carefully planned pitfall
早就预设好的陷阱
There's no point in further discussion.
多说无益
The victor remains to be seen!
鹿死谁手还不一定呢
The fire moth rises,
火蛾起
revealing the truth!
显众生
These envoys are impostors!
这些使臣是假的
I have never fully trusted you either.
我也从未完全信任过你
Now six Imperial Legates
如今六镇府兵的都尉
have all pledged their loyalty to me.
都已唯我是从
Just moments ago,
就在刚刚
they surrounded the palace.
他们带兵围宫
What do you have to fight against me?
你拿什么跟我斗
The tide has turned against you.
如今大势已去
You may regret it now,
你们后悔了
but it's too late!
晚了
Shen Du,
沈渡
you could have been the first among
你本可以是我
my dynasty's founding heroes.
开国第一功臣
Alas.
可惜了
Leave no one alive!
一个不留
Kill them all!
杀
Everything will be fine.
不会有事的
I will protect you.
我会保护你的
You will surely ascend...
你一定会登上
To the throne.
登上皇位的
You will, without a doubt.
你一定会的
I won't let your death be in vain.
我不会让你白死的
General Zhenyuan, you've mobilized
镇远将军
your troops with remarkable speed,
兵行神速
swiftly restoring order.
及时平乱
You truly are the greatest general
不愧是我大苍
defending our empire's borders!
镇守边境的第一大将
[Your Highness,]
贤王殿下
[six field armies]
六镇府兵
[have secretly allied with Lai Luozhi.]
暗中投靠来罗织
[The forces we can mobilize in the city]
城内可调遣的兵力
[are likely insufficient.]
恐难相抵
[The Fire Moth Sect]
如今各郡
[has placed all counties]
都被火蛾门的人
[under surveillance.]
监控动向
[Only one man can turn the tide.]
唯有一人可破此局
[To avoid alarming the enemy,]
未免打草惊蛇
[I hope Your Highness will personally]
还望贤王躬亲相助
[intervene to alleviate the plight of Xiang'an]
解襄安之围
[and quell the unrest in the empire.]
平大苍之乱
Thanks to Your Highness' covert letter;
多亏贤王亲自派人密函
I was alerted to the presence of
传达圣意
traitors in our midst.
想不到朝中竟有人
It seems that some within the court
胆敢勾结通敌
are in league with the enemy, scheming to
妄图制造边境混乱
create turmoil at the border to pin me down.
困制住我
He would never have imagined
他怎么也不会想到
that an elite legion
会有一队精锐
had already set off for Xiang'an!
早已抽身奔赴襄安
Lai Luozhi may have been persuasive,
来罗织蛊惑人心
but he neglected to see that
却不曾想过
the palace
这殿内
is home to my family,
皆是本王至亲之人
with His Majesty being
如今陛下
my very flesh and blood.
更是本王的亲侄
Now, more than ever, as a subject
身为大苍子民
of the empire, we must stand
此时此刻
united with our nation and the people.
定要与国与民同在
We have an endless number of disciples.
我火蛾门徒数不尽
Spanning the entire empire,
大苍之内
all branches of the Fire Moth Sect
火蛾门各分部
are rising up in unison with me today.
今日与我同时揭竿而起
How do you plan to counter this uprising?
你要如何破
Do you intend to have all the citizens
要让所有襄安城的百姓
of Xiang'an perish alongside you?
跟你一同殉葬吗
Lord Shen, the rebel forces outside
大阁领
have been thoroughly crushed!
殿外叛军已全部消灭
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
It's time to surrender!
束手就擒吧
Just moments ago,
就在刚刚
your Fire Moth Sect members have
你部署在各地的火蛾门
all been eradicated in the entire realm.
已全数被剿
The tide has
属于你的大势
already turned.
已去
[On the day of the grand assembly,]
大朝会之日
[Lai Luozhi will undoubtedly]
来罗织必将
[concentrate his forces in the palace.]
集中兵力于皇宫
[Jiang Langxing will relay the news]
江郎行将消息
[to all the delinquents across the land.]
带与各地异良人
[At that moment,]
到时
[It will be time to dismantle]
便是拔除各地
[the Fire Moth Sect's strongholds.]
火蛾门据点之时
All delinquents, on my command!
众异良人听令
Eliminate the Fire Moth Sect,
清理外郡火蛾门
take down all their strongholds,
所有据点
and arrest every cultist!
拿下所有邪教徒
Leave not a single one!
一个都不许放过
Understood!
是
[Mr. Liang, If your design]
梁兄
[for the new crossbow is]
若你绘制的
[successfully produced, with multiple]
新式弓弩制出
[arrows launched simultaneously,]
数箭齐发
[its power will be unparalleled,]
神威无敌
[our forces will be ten times mightier!]
便可以让我军以一敌十
[Then a single elite legion can achieve]
到时只许一队精锐
[victory against overwhelming odds.]
便可以少胜多
Liangs' weaponry are truly remarkable.
梁府的兵器果真玄妙
In this endeavor to restore order,
此次镇乱
you have made invaluable contributions.
梁府功不可没
This is all thanks to Lord Shen,
都是沈兄一直不弃
who's always been there to encourage me.
勉励相助
You pathetic lowlifes!
你们这些蝼蚁
Putting on a show of righteousness,
装模作样
while allowing her to monopolize power.
放任太皇太后独揽朝政
She is incompetent and tyrannical.
昏庸无道
Who is truly responsible for poisoning
荼毒我大苍之本的
the very foundation of our empire?
罪魁祸首是谁
It is her,
是她
Zhou Xu!
周姁
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
you established the Fire Moth Sect,
你建立火蛾门
deceiving and manipulating,
装神弄鬼
harming the loyal and virtuous.
残害忠良
You're responsible for countless deaths.
被你所害之人不计其数
How dare you speak
你有什么资格
with such arrogance here?
在这里大言不惭
The Fire Moth Sect can infiltrate
我火蛾门能在大苍
every corner of the empire
无所不至
Because I have created
是因为我给世人
a beautiful dream of resurrection
创造了一个
for the people!
起死回生的美梦
As mere mortals, who can
生而为人
escape the inevitabilities of death?
谁能逃得过生老病死
Who can avoid the pain of
谁能躲得掉
losing those we hold dear?
失去至亲至爱的痛
From the lowliest to the loftiest,
别说寻常百姓
all must face life's
就是那些达官贵人
unavoidable realities!
又如何
Even Mo Qianzhi had placed his trust in me,
莫谦之不一样听信于我
and acted under my influence!
被我所控行事
You shameless scoundrel.
无耻之徒
I detest people like you,
我就讨厌你这种
who preach righteousness and morality,
满口仁义道德
while considering themselves exceptional!
自命不凡的
You seek to overthrow the monarch;
你妄图颠覆国本
I cannot condone such treachery!
我岂能附逆
If my father were still alive,
若是我父在世
He would have done the same!
也绝不会应允
I'm first and foremost a citizen of
我沈渡先是大苍儿郎
the empire, and only then a son of the Shens!
后才是沈家子
Your father was a fool too!
你爹也是个蠢货
[I seek only to uphold a clear conscience,]
只求无愧于心
[And to be deserving of the people.]
无愧于黎民百姓
[How could I ever]
岂能和你们
[associate myself with the likes of you?]
沆瀣一气
He believed he was upright, yet he didn't
他自以为守正不阿
realize he already made countless enemies.
却不想早已树敌无数
Many wanted to
想要置他于死地的
see him dead!
大有人在
You,
你啊
are just as foolish as your father!
同你那个爹一样蠢
I've only employed a few tricks,
我不过是用了点小手段
and I was able to make the Shen Family
就能让你们沈家
fall into the inferno!
万劫不复
Your treachery against
残害忠良
the honorable is unparalleled!
丧心病狂
You dream of being in power,
你妄想当道
but even God cannot tolerate that!
天理都难容
God?
天理
Let me ask you,
那我问你
who determined the Shen Family's crime?
沈家的罪是谁裁断的
Who is truly responsible
残害沈家的真凶
for the destruction of the Shen Family?
到底应该算是谁
Zhou xu,
周姁
you manipulate the throne
你挟这个小哑巴皇帝
through this voiceless emperor,
把持朝政
have you ever been haunted
可曾夜半惊醒
by your disloyalty to the late emperor,
觉得愧对先帝
my father?
我的父皇
I am supposed to be the chosen one,
我才是天选之子
born of the supreme bloodline!
拥有至高无上的血脉
Today,
今日
I shall reinstate the rightful order
我定要为萧家王朝
for the Xiao Family and the throne!
拨乱反正
[The late emperor?]
先帝
[Could it be that he is...]
难道他是
I am the son of the late emperor
我乃先帝
and Consort Shu.
淑妃之子
Phoenix leading nine chicks;
凤引九雏
peace in the world.
天下太平
Purify the source
正本清源
and reconstruct the realm!
再定乾坤
So,
难道
the prophecy
国师预言
indeed has a second half?
真有下半
[That statement is falsified.]
此言有误
Chief Clerk of the Ministry of Justice, Yan Xing,
刑部都官主事颜幸
greets Your Majesty
拜见圣上
and Your Royal Highness.
拜见太皇太后
Please rise, my lady.
爱卿请起
On that day, the Royal Advisor's
回禀太皇太后
prophecy indeed had a second half,
当日国师预言确有下半
but it was never presented.
未曾来得及呈上
Yet, it's nothing like what he said.
却绝非方才来罗织所言
What proof do you have?
有何凭证
The true prophecy
真正的预言
is hidden within this garment.
就藏在这小衫之中
The calm sky (Bi) and setting (Luo) sun
碧空落日
hide the coming (Lai) danger?
来祟反之
That's right.
没错
He made a prophecy that day,
国师当日作出预言
and the latter half
后半段
refers to the hidden wicked ambitions
意指朝中
among the officials.
潜藏的狼子野心
It serves as a warning to Your Highness
意在提醒太皇太后
to be wary of those around you.
提防身边人
Lai Luozhi has been meticulously running
来罗织苦心经营
the Fire Moth Sect for years,
火蛾门多年
with cultists secretly causing chaos.
邪教徒暗中作祟
The Royal Advisor noticed the signs,
国师察觉端倪
and thus
更是因此
began to suspect
对来罗织的身份
Lai Luozhi's identity.
产生了怀疑
But due to a lack of evidence, he had
苦于没有证据
no choice but to convey his suspicions
国师只好将他的怀疑
to the world through the prophecy.
以预言来告知世人
He may have realized that he was being
可能是发现自己的行踪
secretly monitored by Lai Luozhi.
已被来罗织暗中监控
He had to embroider the prophecy
他只好将预言
onto the brocade,
绣于锦布之上
concealed within its patterns,
藏于花纹之中
and bide his time until
再寻合适的时机
the moment was right.
传递出来
But unexpectedly,
却不想
he was silenced by the
被来罗织派出的人
assassin sent by Lai Luozhi.
先一步暗杀灭口
But God has a way of ensuring justice,
但天网恢恢 疏而不漏
the brocade with the prophecy was
写有预言下半的锦布
fortuitously found by the illiterate
刚巧被不识字的芫娘
Yuan Niang who used it
当做好布料捡了去
as the lining of a baby's garment,
做成了婴儿小衫的内布
and thus it remained.
就这么留了下来
[If Yuan Niang is just an ordinary woman,]
若是芫娘只是普通民妇
[how could she afford]
怎么能买得起
[such fabric?]
这种布料呢
[This fabric]
这内里的布料
[Is certainly not something]
绝不是寻常人家
[an ordinary family could afford.]
能够寻到的
The Royal Advisor is stubborn,
国师迂腐
and he refuses to see reason.
冥顽不灵
Are we really going to entrust
难道真要把江山
the empire to a witless child?
交给无智小儿不成
Or to that ineffectual Prince Xian?
还是那个窝囊的贤王
Or to the arrogant Princess Ying?
骄横跋扈的永安公主
As long as the Empress Dowager
只要太皇太后
is still in power,
还在朝一日
no one's future is secured!
就没人能自安
Once upon a time,
曾几何时
wasn't Princess Runing
那汝宁长公主
also of supreme status?
不也一样至尊至贵
But just because someone changed
不过是被人
the embroidery pattern on her clothes,
调换了衣衫的绣样
she was accused of exceeding regulations.
就被指附逆僭越
And ended up in her current situation.
落得如今的下场
So it turns out
原来
Princess Runing
汝宁长公主
was also framed by you?
也是被你设计构陷
If it weren't for your suspicions,
若非你疑心生鬼
how could I have succeeded so easily?
我怎能轻易得逞
Just blame yourself!
要怪就怪你自己
You, Zhou Xu,
你周姁
are the true threat to my Xiao Family!
才是我萧氏宗室的大患
As a descendant of the Xiao Family,
我身为萧家子孙
I must restore order for the empire!
自当为大苍拨乱反正
The throne rightfully belongs to me;
皇位于我
it is God's will.
乃是天经地义
I am the most legitimate prince to ascend!
我才是得位最正的皇子
But you are not a son of the late emperor;
可你并非先帝之子
you were conceived by Consort Shu
而是先帝宠妃淑妃
in an affair with someone else.
与他人私通所生
Consort Shu was originally
淑妃本是南琅国
the carefree Princess Biluo of Nanlang,
无忧无虑的碧落郡主
who fell in love with General Kongshan,
当年与空山将军相爱
and they pledged to be together for life.
私定终身
It was supposed to be a beautiful story,
本是一段佳话
But her father, the king,
却被她的父王南琅王
forced her to marry into the empire
一道圣旨逼嫁大苍
and wed the late emperor for an alliance.
同先帝和亲
She swore she'd rather die than comply.
碧落郡主誓死不从
So in a fit of rage,
南琅王一怒之下
the king executed General Kongshan, and
杀了空山将军
threatened her with the lives of his clan.
更以其一族性命威胁
She could only bribe the palace servants
碧落只能买通内侍
to escape the inspection,
逃过宫廷检查
and became known as
成为了人们口中的
Consort Shu.
那个淑妃
From then on,
从此
she lost her love,
失去了她的爱情
and also her name.
也失去了她的姓名
Her reason for continuing to live was
而她活下去的理由
not only to protect the general's clan
除了保全空山将军一族
but also for the child she was carrying,
更是为了她腹中
his offspring.
怀着的空山将军的子嗣
This can't be true!
这不可能是真的
This can't be...
不可能
My mother would never have lied to me!
我母妃不会骗我的
I am a descendant of the Xiao Family!
我是萧家子孙
I am the son of the late emperor!
是大苍先帝的皇子
Back then, Nanlang
当年南琅
escorted Princess Biluo
护送碧落郡主
to the empire. During the journey,
来大苍的随行中
someone noticed she was unwell
有人察觉到她身体有恙
and discovered that she was pregnant.
发现了此事
She tried to silence this man,
便被她暗中灭口
but fortunately, he managed to escape.
好在此人侥幸逃生
Lai Luozhi,
来罗织
you are not of the Xiao bloodline.
你根本就不是萧氏血脉
from start to finish,
你的人生
your life has been a lie.
彻头彻尾就是一场谎言
Impossible!
不可能
My mother would never have lied to me!
母妃不会骗我的
You are her minions,
你们这些庸碌鼠辈
every last one of you!
都是她周姁的走狗
Your lies and treachery
你们捏造诳话
are designed to stop
昧地瞒天
me from taking the throne
都是为了
and restoring
阻止我登基即位
order to the realm!
匡扶天下
Like moths drawn to the flame.
飞蛾扑火
Fleeting...
朝生
in life!
暮死
After all,
原来
"Like moths drawn to the flame"
飞蛾扑火
this is nothing but a dream...
终究是一场大梦啊
Open it.
开门
Understood!
是
Greetings, Lord Jing.
见过景内卫
Lai Luozhi's faction has been dealt with.
来党已伏法
By order of Lord Commander,
大阁领命我来
I am here to escort you all home.
速速送各位回家
We ask for your understanding
这几日辛苦了
if the Imperial Guard
内卫府若有怠慢
has not been attentive.
还请各位海涵
That's wonderful!
太好了
Lord Jing,
景内卫
Lord Commander confined us
您客气了
in Imperial Guard's
大阁领把我们
dungeon to genuinely
关入内卫府大牢
protect us from the
实则是保护
threats of Lai Luozhi's faction.
我们免受来党之害
We are
我等
fully aware of that!
岂会不知啊
Right, right!
是啊 是啊 是啊
Shen Du,
沈渡
you need to understand,
你得明白
once the die is cast,
开弓之箭
there's no turning back.
可就没有回头路了
I have made up my mind.
我想好了
Lady Xu,
劳烦徐内司
please inform Her Royal Highness.
通传太皇太后
Lady Yan, please come another day.
颜主事改日再来吧
Her Royal Highness
太皇太后一会儿
will summon me shortly.
要召见本官
She won't be available for you.
已无空见你
The officials from Lai Luozhi's faction
来党官员
have been ordered to face scrutiny.
都已被下旨查办
What is your purpose in
你今日见太皇太后
visiting Her Royal Highness today?
究竟所为何事
I have quelled the rebels and rendered
本阁领平定乱党
meritorious service to the empire.
为大苍立下汗马功劳
I have come to request a reward.
问太皇太后讨要赏赐
Do I need to discuss this with someone
需要和一个
of your status, a lowly rank-six official?
从六品官说吗
I shall join Lord Shen in the meeting
那我更要与沈大阁领
with Her Royal Highness.
一同觐见了
The effort was not solely yours.
诛伐乱党非你一人之功
I have contributed as well.
我也出了力
You cannot claim
这赏
all the credit.
你可不能独得
If you want to seek rewards,
想要讨赏
you should ask your direct superior
让你们刑部主官
to submit an request for it.
写奏折呈上
Lady Yan,
颜主事
you should return.
回吧
It's unheard of to ask for a reward
哪有人讨赏
and present a gift at the same time.
还要自己送礼的
I believe this box contains the booklet
我想这锦盒里装的
that has caused a stir
是那份震动朝野的
among all the officials.
证据吧
You came today
你今日来
for Shen Family...
是为了沈家
Lady Yan,
颜主事
choose your words carefully.
慎言
Now that we are divorced,
如今你我已经和离
you're no longer my wife.
你已不是沈家妇
The affairs of my family
我沈府的事
are not for you to interfere with!
轮不到你来管
Fine.
好
Even if I am no longer your wife,
就算我不是沈家妇
I will still pursue this to the end.
这件事我也要管到底
I came here
我站在这里
not as
不是以
your wife,
你沈渡妻子的身份
But as a chief clerk
而是我以
of the Ministry of Justice.
刑部都官主事之职
I'm here to overturn the wrongful
重审冤案
conviction and restore the innocents' names.
还清白于人间
And that is my aspiration.
这是我颜六娘的理想
Lord Shen,
沈大阁领
Her Royal Highness summons you.
太皇太后召您进去
As an official of the Ministry of Justice,
你既在刑部为官
you should know better
更应该清楚
that Her Royal Highness is summoning
太皇太后召见的
the commander of Imperial Guard.
是本阁领
You have no right to come uninvited.
你岂有不请自来之理
Are you planning to barge in her chamber?
莫非你要闯殿不成
If you go in alone,
你若一人进去
then we shall not see each other again.
你我便不必再见
His Majesty has caught a slight cold
皇上偶感风寒
and will take a day to recuperate.
歇息一日
He will hold the assembly tomorrow.
明日再朝
My lords,
众爱卿
Do you have any reports to present?
可有本要奏啊
Qiao Wenzhi,
乔文智
you are in charge of Gannan.
你代管甘南道
Do you
今日
have anything to report today?
可有事要奏
Your Royal Highness,
禀太皇太后
with the Lai faction eradicated,
自来党伏法以后
the realm enjoys peace and prosperity.
我大苍皆是民康物阜
Gannan is also thriving.
甘南道更是欣欣向荣
We are truly in an era of peace.
实是天下太平
There is nothing to report.
无事要奏
A fine time of peace indeed!
好一个天下太平啊
The Lai faction has been vanquished,
来党是伏法了
but this booklet they left behind
可这留下来的册子
is quite informative.
有用得很
Qiao Wenzhi, you secretly imported
乔文智
goods from Xichen, entering the empire
你私自从西辰贩货
through the Gannan to profit.
经甘南道入境大苍牟利
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
this is a false accusation!
冤枉啊
The so-called evidence
那甘南道的乱党
left by the rebels in Gannan
留下的所谓证据
cannot be trusted!
不能为据
It's not reliable!
不可信啊
Unreliable?
不可信
Then
那
how would you explain
这两本阴阳账册
those two sets of accounts?
你作何解释
Those were not from the Lai faction!
这可不是来党递交的
The accounts for the Ming Hall reconstruction
明堂重建
reveals a discrepancy between
实账和假账
the ledgers, nearly doubling the cost!
足足差了两倍
However, the corruption in the Ming Hall
可是明堂
involves officials from all ministries,
各部都有参与
not just...
非下官一人
Qiao Wenzhi,
乔文智
stop your nonsense!
休要胡言 休要胡言
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
Qiao Wenzhi
乔文智
has been my subordinate for years.
乃老臣下属官员
He has been blinded by greed,
他因利欲熏心
embezzling funds,
贪墨朝廷银两
committing a grave crime.
犯下了大罪
This was the result of my oversight.
都是臣失察之责
I seek Your Highness' penalties.
望太皇太后责罚
Result of your oversight?
失察之责
Lord Zhang, your erudition is immense,
张相你真是学富五车
and your choice of words is impeccable.
用词精妙啊
Qiao Wenzhi
可这乔文智
has been utterly loyal to you.
对你是忠心耿耿啊
Most of the
明堂贪墨
embezzled funds
多数都进了
ended up in your pocket.
你张行微的口袋
Zhang Xingwei,
张行微
Do you have anything to say for yourself?
你还有什么要说
I...
臣
have nothing to say.
无话可说
Prince Xian.
贤王
Mother.
母后
Let me ask you,
哀家问你
how should we deal with him?
该如何处置他
Your Highness' wisdom is unmatched,
母后英明决断
and will surely make a decisive judgment.
自有主张
I'll make a decisive judgment?
哀家自有主张
I am asking you now,
我现在问你
what is your judgment?
是怎么主张
Since childhood, I have studied under him,
儿臣自幼拜张相为师
He has consistently set a high standard,
张相一直以身作则
instructing me to place the
教育儿臣
interests of the empire first.
万事要以社稷为重
I do not believe Lord Zhang
儿臣不相信
would have committed such a crime
张相为区区白银
for a mere handful of silver.
犯下此罪
There must be more to this
此案
than meets the eye.
必有隐情
Oh, Prince Xian,
贤王啊贤王
you are so misguided.
你好糊涂啊
That's merely a facade I have maintained,
都是本相在惺惺作态
deceiving you for all these years,
瞒了你这么多年
and yet, you still plead for my defense.
你还在为本相求情
Well,
好啊
What a touching bond of mentor and pupil!
好一段感人的师生情啊
Lord Zhang,
张相
let me explain on your behalf.
那哀家替你说了吧
You received the money,
你得此银两
yet you did not spend it on yourself.
全未花在自己身上
You used it
你在朝中
to buy off other officials,
收买同党
in order to have them
为的是
support Prince Xian alongside you!
和你一起来支持贤王
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
now that it has come to this,
事已至此
I
臣
will no longer conceal the truth.
就不再隐瞒了
His Highness,
此事
Prince Xian,
他贤王殿下
truly knows nothing about it.
确实一无所知
It was all my doing.
都是老臣一人所为
Please grant me the death penalty
请太皇太后赐臣死罪
to serve as a warning to others!
以儆效尤
Do you think
你以为舍你一条命
that your death
你的罪孽
will erase your crimes?
就一笔勾销了吗
The innocent officials who
因你而家破人亡
died unjustly due to your actions
含冤屈死的忠臣
can never be brought back!
他们永远都无法复活了
Lord Shen,
沈爱卿
present it!
呈上来吧
[By the will of God,]
应天顺时
[we hereby declare: ]
受兹明命
[traitor Shen Bingzhu,]
罪臣沈秉烛
[guilty of colluding with the enemy,]
与敌暗通书信
[burning our military granaries,]
烧毁我军粮仓
[revealing weapon blueprints,]
泄露兵器图谱
[conspiring with foreign powers,]
里通外国
[and committing treason!]
叛军通敌
[His crimes are punishable by death.]
其罪当诛
[The Shens are sentenced to confinement and banishment.]
沈家满门幽禁发配
[Let this be known to all!]
令远近知悉
[My desire is not for eternal glory,]
沈某不求扬名于后世
[but to live with a clear conscience,]
只求无愧于心
[faithful to the populace.]
无愧于黎民百姓
[Master was inherently modest,]
老师沈秉烛生性淡泊
[always seeking to avoid court intrigues.]
从不愿卷入朝堂纷争
[His only concern was for the people.]
他关心的只有百姓
[Regardless of who it was in power,]
不管任何人在任何位置
[he simply did what he believed was right.]
他只做自己应做之事
[Peace for the people was his only wish.]
只要百姓安宁
[I, nourished by monarch's bounty,]
沈某食天子俸禄
[stands ready to shoulder His Majesty's burdens,]
自然为圣上分忧
[with no fear of death.]
万死不辞
I, Shen Du,
臣沈渡
am here to seek justice for my father,
为我父亲沈秉烛
Shen Bingzhu.
伸冤
[The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du]
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
[accuses my father]
检举我父
[of colluding with foreign powers]
里通外国
[and committing treason!]
叛军通敌
[I hereby report!]
我检举
[The traitor Shen Bingzhu's son, Shen Du]
罪臣沈秉烛之子沈渡
[accuses my father]
检举我父
[of colluding with foreign powers]
里通外国
Am here to seek justice for my father,
为我父亲沈秉烛
Shen Bingzhu.
伸冤
Sixteen years ago,
十六年前
Our empire was at war with Xichen.
我大苍和西辰交战
When we urgently needed provisions,
正急需粮草之时
the main granary storing food supplies
储存粮草的主粮仓
suddenly
突然
caught fire for unknown reasons,
烧起了一场莫名的大火
burning all
把我大苍的粮草
our provisions.
烧得精光
Shen Bingzhu, who was entrusted with
看守粮草的沈秉烛
our provisions, had been discovered
被查出有通敌私信
to be a traitor and sentenced to death.
被治重罪
This
这
piece of sack bearing the granary seal
带有当年粮仓印鉴的
from that year
粮草袋
should have been completely burned.
本应该是烧毁殆尽的
Yet it appeared
可却在
in Gannan from thousands of miles away.
千里之外的甘南道出现
The letter of collusion,
你递给先帝的
which you submitted to the late emperor,
那封通敌书信
was discovered to be
被发现
not of Shen Bingzhu's own hand.
并非沈秉烛本人所作
Lord Zhang,
张相
what do you have to say for yourself?
你说这是什么原因啊
When the war broke out,
当年开战
my disciple came to me,
我的门生找到我
and I learned
我才知道
that he colluded with local officials
他与当地官员纠集
to sell off grains from imperial granary.
倒卖国库粮草
They bought it at low prices
在价低时买入
and sold it at high prices the following
等来年价高时再卖出
year, profiting from the difference.
从中挣取差价
Unexpectedly,
怎料
the war with Xichen suddenly broke out,
那西辰战事突然爆发
and the provisions in the granary
国库的粮草
had been sold out.
已被他们卖光
Only a pile of straw remained...
只剩下一堆茅草
Oh, Lord Zhang,
张相啊张相
I never imagined until now that this,
哀家至今未曾想到
which could shake the foundation of the
这能动摇大苍国本的事
state, would actually be related to you.
竟然与你有关
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
I never expected either,
老臣也万万没有想到
that one day
会有一日
I would cover up
老臣为了遮掩
my student's crimes
门徒的罪行
by committing such a heinous act.
做出这丧尽天良的事情
It was I who ordered someone
是我
to imitate Lord Shen's handwriting
派人模仿沈侍郎的笔迹
to come up with that treasonous letter.
写了那封通敌的书信
You forged the treasonous letter.
你伪造了通敌书信
Then what
那这场大火
caused the fire?
因何而起
Lord Zhang,
张相
do you want me to investigate further?
你是否要哀家再查
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
this was all my doing.
这都是臣一人之私
May this investigation end with me.
死罪就到臣一家为止吧
To delve deeper could
若再查下去
destabilize the core of our empire.
就会动摇我大苍之本
It could potentially
到时候
expose influential figures
投鼠忌器
within our empire,
无功而返
achieving nothing but losing much!
得不偿失啊 太皇太后
Influential figures?
投鼠忌器
Who are
这器
these individuals?
指的谁
There are certain things
有些话
that I
臣
must leave unspoken...
不能明言
[Lord Shen, please.]
沈大阁领请
[Do you really have so much faith in me?]
你就这么信哀家
[Aren't you afraid that you]
你就不怕
[and this box might disappear together?]
你和这锦盒一起消失吗
[Over the years,]
这些年
[I have witnessed Your Highness devote]
臣亲见太皇太后
[yourself to the welfare of the people.]
为大苍民生殚精竭虑
[I believe you will make]
臣相信您会作出
[a fair and just decision.]
公正的决断
[I am willing to]
臣不惜
[bet my life on it.]
以命相搏
Let me
那
clarify for you.
哀家替你明言吧
Before Lord Shen took over the granary,
在沈侍郎接管粮仓之前
the local official stationed there
驻守的当地官员
was my nephew,
是哀家的侄子
Zhou Miao!
周淼
Fearing that the matter would be exposed,
他唯恐事情败露
he colluded with the Lai faction
不惜勾结来党
using the Ignition Craft from Jinwu
用金乌助燃术
to set our granary ablaze,
将我大苍的粮仓
burning it to ashes!
付之一炬啊
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
you...
您
Someone!
来人
Detain him for a thorough investigation!
把周淼拖出去好好审
Any member of the Zhou Family implicated
凡周家涉事者
will face harsher punishment!
一律罪加一等
Your Royal Highness, mercy!
太皇太后 饶命啊
Spare me!
饶命啊
Prince Xian,
贤王
I ask you again,
哀家再问你
how should we
张相
deal with Lord Zhang?
该如何处置
I humbly request that Your Highness
儿臣拜请母后
mete out justice to Zhang Xingwei
按律处置张行微
but I also
但
implore you to consider his past merits
张氏家族族人
and show leniency to
还望母后念及过往功绩
the members of the Zhang Family.
从轻发落